and so we have it's בכורות ג' Bechorot Gimmel but we start
at the bottom of page ע' ב' Ayin Bais and before we
actually start reading the גמרא Gemara I need to take out two
minutes to refer to a very important תוספות Tosafot the גמרא Gemara
at the end of yesterday spoke about a statement of אבוה דשמואל
Avuha DeShmuel that a person is not allowed to go into partnership
with a non-Jew because you would have to I'm telling you because
if the non-Jew was to if you had to try to if
there's a question about if people were being honest and you would
make somebody take an oath then you would have the non-Jew take
an oath and his oath would be in the name of his
god and you would transgress having forced him to to use the
name of a of an idolatrous god of a עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah in a way that shows honor and respect and recognition of
that god and that is based on the פסוק Pasuk of לא
ישמע על פיך Lo Yishama Al Picha the name of other gods
shall not be heard on your lips which is understood by the
rabbis to mean which is understood by the rabbis to mean that
you cannot even cause others to say them in that fashion now
that does not mean that you cannot say the name of other
gods like I can say Zeus I didn't transgress I hope not
but what it means is that you cannot say them in a
context which shows that you are recognizing them as gods which goes
to the whole issue by the way about whether people's reluctance or
not to say Jesus there's a famous story that in Rav Soloveitchik's
שיעור Shiur somebody was once saying you know אותו האיש Oto HaIsh
ישו Yeshu and you know he was going on and on Rav
said what do you mean Jesus so
but I personally will not say if you would Jesus's last name
because that actually although technically it only means Messiah it doesn't mean
God but that is a name that basically is used to to
refer to the divinity and to acknowledge the divinity so I don't
say that that's one issue which I'm sure people want to discuss
but I don't want to discuss right now which is
saying the name of other gods within a particular context but now
within that issue we get to תוספות Tosafot because תוספות Tosafot tries
to figure out wait a minute can't go into partnership with non-Jews
because you'll make them take oaths how do we go into partnership
with Christians and we do it all the time and not only
that not only do we go into partnership with them but we
actually do make them take oaths when you know and they will
take an oath in the name of you know they'll say in
the name of God in the name of their saints and so
on how is that allowed and תוספות Tosafot in order to come
up with an answer for this suggests says an answer which has
which has profound influence in the development of הלכה's Halacha's attitude towards
Christianity so I I direct your attention to the bottom of the
תוספות Tosafot on ע' ב' Ayin Bais the תוספות Tosafot starts with
the word שמא Shema and where תוספות Tosafot says like this עוד
פירש רבינו תם Od Peirush Rabbeinu Tam it is about ten lines
from the bottom the line starts with the word לא היו נזהרין
בהן Lo Hayu Nizharin Bahen okay so first that's just another interesting
point which he makes which is talking about that רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam points out that if you look in other גמרות Gemarot it
seems like Jews were going into business with non-Jews and that this
was not a law that really was even that much kept in
the time of the גמרא Gemara so which is an interesting question
as well which is not which is you know goes to the
general question that we raised before about sort of things that are
stated as הלכה Halacha but then how does that interact with common
practice so one point רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam makes is that it
seems that this whole law was not so much kept in practice
is
this on the books
well whatever maybe there was those that disagreed with it implicitly it
wasn't accepted by everybody but what's more important for us is the
next line where תוספות Tosafot
says עוד פירש רבינו תם בזמן הזה כולם נשבעים בקדשים Od Peirush
Rabbeinu Tam Bizman Hazeh Kulam Nishba'in Bekadeshim nowadays when Christians take oaths
they take oaths in the name of their saints not in the
name of Jesus
so that is not אלוהים אחרים Elohim Acheirim because it's the name
of a saint it's not a name of somebody that is given
divinity ואין תופסים בהם אלוהות Ve'ein Tofsim Bahem Elohut they don't believe
their saints are gods I mean they believe they're holy but they
don't treat them give them divinity so taking an oath in the
name of a saint is not in the name of another god
okay that's answer number one ואף על פי שמזכירים עמהם שם שמים
Ve'af Al Pi Shemazkirim Imahem Shem Shamayim
although they also say God right if anybody I remember all this
from the Shakespeare's Henry V particularly the movie by Kenneth Branagh production
where they're about to storm whatever the city is or whatever he
says in the name of God and who is it Saint Saint
George something like that anyway so he said they take an oath
it's not only Saint so-and-so it's an oath in the name of
God and Saint so-and-so so God and their God is not the
same idea as our God וכונתם לדבר אחר Vekavanatam Ledavar Acheir and
what they're thinking when they say God although it's the same word
is not exactly what we think when we say God מכל מקום
Mikol Makom he says nevertheless אין זה שם עבודת כוכבים Ein Zeh
Shem Avodat Kochavim
it's not the name of another god why כי דעתם לעושה שמים
וארץ Ki Da'atam Le'oseh Shamayim Va'aretz
he says look we say God they say God and don't tell
me that okay but they're thinking something else no actually when they
say God as opposed to saying Jesus they're thinking of in their
mind God the Father which is essentially is our concept of God
the creator of heaven and earth so saints they're not treating as
God God is actually is God the the Christian idea of Jesus
which is for us what is not acceptable is not part of
their oath so it's not a problem at all you could have
them take an oath but wait a minute so therefore it's not
a problem of having them take an oath. Okay, so we sort
of managed to get around all that. Now so far, it's just
a problem that solves the issue of oaths, it doesn't have larger
significance. Then he goes on and says like this. ואף על גב
דמשתתף שם שמים ודבר אחר, Ve'af al gav demishtatef shem shamayim vedavar
acher,
now one minute, there's a problem. In their oath they say God
and Saint so-and-so. That's combining God's name with something else. A Jew
cannot say in the name of God and heaven and earth. Can't
take an oath that way because that equates something created with God
and you can't put them together in an oath.
That in the name of God creator of heaven and earth, right
you could do?
No. Oh, creator of, yes. But you can't say God and and
take an oath in the name of something else plus God because
obviously that puts them in the same category. So that is forbidden
as an oath. He says אין כאן לפני עור לא תתן מכשול,
Ein kan lifnei iver lo titein michshol, you're not causing them to
sin by taking that oath. דבני נח לא הוזהרו אכך, Debnei Noach
lo huzharu akach, a non-Jew is not prohibited from taking that type
of an oath, combining God's name with another with something else. ולדידן
Uledidan and for us to cause them to do it, בשלמא Beshalma
we can't cause them to take an oath in the name of
an idolatrous God, but to cause them to take an oath in
the name of God and heaven and earth or God and a
saint, to take an oath of God and say something else in
that oath, לא אשכחן איסור בגרם שיתוף, Lo ashkechan issur begram shituf,
there's no prohibition of us causing them to do that. You can
tell them to do that, right?
No, so basically there's no problem with them. It's only a problem
for us to combine God and something else in an oath. So
it's not the name of another God and we're not combining and
they're not and the fact that they're saying God and the saint
is not a problem for them and therefore שמע ישראל Shma Yisrael
they can take the oath. So read that way, which is the
right way to read תוספות, Tosafot, all he he solves brilliantly the
problem of taking their taking oaths and being in partnership with them.
And also it's interesting because it for one point it's is a
תוספות Tosafot that although תוספות Tosafot consistently
and generally throughout the ראשונים Rishonim consistently Christianity is is defined as
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it's a תוספות Tosafot that acknowledges if you
would the important area of overlap that within the concept of God
the Father, you know, basically it is fundamentally the same belief and
there and that's important in acknowledging that. But what became particularly important
about this תוספות Tosafot was the way it was misinterpreted. Because when
תוספות Tosafot says there is no prohibition for non-Jews to to combine
God and something else in an oath, if you drop the in
an oath and and they're talking about Christians and you say there's
no prohibition on non-Jews to combine God and something else, right? That
that can automatically be understood as for Christians there is no problem
to believe in the concept of the Trinity. As long as they
have a belief in ultimate עושה שמים וארץ, Oseh Shamayim Va'aretz, an
ultimate all-powerful God, that they have other concepts associated with that and
a Trinity whatever, that is not a problem for them. It's a
problem for us, for us it's still עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but
for them that's okay, that's not עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And this
תוספות Tosafot became interpreted already by the time of the רמ״א, Rema,
which is very important because that's, you know, authoritative for אשכנזים Ashkenazim
in the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch to to add create an idea
of a dual standard that for what defines עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
For Jews the Christian faith is עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but for
non-Jews it is not. And that actually led to an important shift
in almost a quasi-pluralism,
you know, not really pluralistic, it's not like it's all the same
type of a thing, but a quasi-pluralistic attitude which is that when
dealing with issues about the Christianity we no longer have to say
that they are עובדי עבודה זרה. Ovedei Avodah Zarah. Now you could
still maintain the boundary that for us it's עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
which maintains the boundary and the taboo. Don't take don't think it's
okay for a Jew, it's still עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah for a
Jew. But it at least leads to more of a non-judgmentalism
and a more fundamentally, you know, sort of inclusive and a little
bit not only practically allows for certain הלכות Halachot to not be
as as, you know, exclusionary of non of Christians, but also for
a more sort of fundamentally, you know, type of an inclusive mentality.
So the misinterpretation of this תוספות Tosafot has been extremely influential in
the הלכתי Halachic development and the thought towards how sort towards Christians
and Christianity. That's what I wanted to share. Totally unrelated to what
we're about to learn in the דף Daf but I could not
pass up this תוספות Tosafot without without mentioning it. Bobby, yes.
Okay, the first there are two things that come to mind. Number
one, I don't see why there's a problem from the very beginning
because one doesn't have to use God at all. One can say
I give you my word as a human being.
Okay, Bobby,
that's all very lovely but that didn't, you know, that and 50
cents or two dollars will get you a cup of coffee in
the time of תוספות Tosafot and, you know, there's a reason also
in court why you put your hand on a Bible and you
take an oath because because within those contexts of business you could
not trust somebody. The way that you had a sense you were
able to if you were suspecting somebody of stealing from you or,
you know, or cheating on the books, then they're taking an oath
in the name of their God was the way of keeping them
honest.
Okay, so let's just assume even in those days there were people
who were atheists, they put their hands on anything.
Bobby, I don't know what the answer is. All I know is
that in the time of there were very few atheists in the
time of תוספות Tosafot and in those times that was the way
that these issues were dealt with. That's all I can say.
Is that why the תוספות Tosafot was a deliberate misinterpretation? Is there
any indication?
I don't know.
I don't. There's no evidence ever that there's a double definition, double
standard of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but you know, sometimes how even
when not intentionally, you know, the way we're reading texts is influenced
by, you know, subconsciously by all the other sort of ways of
culture and a lot of things. So I there's never an indication
that was a that was a intentional misinterpretation. And if you read
אחרונים Achronim nowadays, I would say the overwhelming percentage are not even
aware that that's a misinterpretation of תוספות. Tosafot. They'll just say, you
know, and according to תוספות, Tosafot, whatever, different definition of עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, da da da da da. So it really has entered
into the very profoundly into the discourse of הלכה. Halacha. Yes.
What about getting around what about the partnership
the fact that it's going to be worked on שבת? Shabbat? What
about that? But that's only about selling your what do you mean?
No, no, if you enter, you know,
oh, not the issue of הלכות שבת. Hilchot Shabbat. What about that?
Something you do type of sale over שבת Shabbat or whatever. That's
not our discussion.
Yes, it's not our discussion. Yes.
If there's a parallel at a certain stage, שבועות Shvuos lose their
meaning in the context of general society, did חז"ל Chazal react to
that by kind of removing the שבועות Shvuos system?
Well, that's a different issue, which is that, you know, but that's
the opposite. Amongst Jews, שבועות Shvuos were always so powerful, even to
take a שבועה Shvuah in truth they wouldn't take a שבועה. Shvuah.
But this was about trying to keep other people, non-Jews, honest. How
they dealt with that in business once that starts happening, I don't
know.
Okay, so I was going to ask if there was a parallel
if this becomes a moot law once the שבועות...
Shvuos... I don't know. But it doesn't matter. תוספות Tosafot already made
it in. But it could be, you're right, if שבועות Shvuos stop
being the way in which people are kept honest, then the prohibition
of going into business would would obviously should obviously drop by the
wayside, yes.
Can you please clarify the misinterpretation?
The misinterpretation is תוספות Tosafot says there's no problem for non-Jews to
combine the name of God and something else in an oath, and
that's misinterpreted to mean there's no problem for non-Jews to believe in
a faith in a
that combines a creator God with other with other gods or other
concepts. So to have a Trinity type of a faith is not
a problem for non-Jews. Okay, now with that, yes?
Is it a coincidence that the same תוספות Tosafot popularized the notion
of שיתוף Shituf does not mean so much?
That's that's the part I skipped over. Okay, now let's go on.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, back to back to our דף.
Daf.
So now we get to the more somewhat mundane question about whether
what the whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן, Rabbanan, what
their position is. If you remember that was the discussion yesterday about
selling a cow for its children, whether that is a prohibition of
selling animals to a non-Jew. So let's take a look. תא שמע,
Tashma, four lines from the bottom, middle of the line. רבי יהודה
אומר המקבל בהמה מן העובד כוכבים וילדה. Rabbi Yehuda Omer, hamakabel behemah
min ha'oved kochavim veyaldah. If somebody takes a
an animal from a non-Jew, מקבל בקבלנות, mekabel bekablanut, in order to
for the sake of raising the children and splitting the children, and
it gives birth, מעלין אותו בשום ויוצא ונותן חצי דמיו לכהן. ma'alin
oto beshom veyotze venoten chatzi damav lakohen. So you estimate the value
of the child and you give half of it to the כהן
Kohen because of בכור. Bechor.
This is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says that an ownership of
a non-Jew does not exempt you, and you give for your portion.
ונותן בקבלה, venoten bekabalah, if you give the animal to a non-Jew
to raise the kids, and he gets half the kids, אף על
פי כן רשאי, af al pi chen rashai, you're not allowed, קונסין
אותו עד עשרה בדמיו, kotzin oto ad asar bedamav, we fine him
ten times in order to buy back the animal or buy back
the kid. ונותן כל דמיו לכהן, venoten kol damav lakohen, and because
we're fining you, you have to give not only the half the
value of the kid of the firstborn to the כהן, Kohen, but
the whole value of the firstborn. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, fine. וחכמים
אומרים כל זמן שיד עובד כוכבים באמצע פטור מן הבכורה. Vachachamim omrim,
kol zman sheyad oved kochavim be'emtza, patur min habechorah. And now we
see the the more sort of central debate, that the Sages say
that as long as a non-Jew is a part owner, you are
fully exempt. Now, for our issue, top of ג' עמוד א', Gimmel
Amud Aleph, for our issue about whether what do you call it
about whether selling an animal for its kids is prohibited, presumably that's
exactly what you did here. You sold the mother and to give
the non-Jew a right in the kids, so he owns the mother
for half of the kids, and we said that you have transgressed.
So you see that that is prohibited. מאי לאו בהמה, mai lav
behemah, don't we see that you have transgressed what you have to
do is buy back because of the animal that was sold for
the kids? So selling an animal even just for the kids is
included in the prohibition. So
the
גמרא Gemara says, לא, עובר, lo, ubar, no, the problem was was
that it was already pregnant and you sold the fetus. So selling
a mother for future kids is not prohibited, but selling the existing
fetus is, which is what we said yesterday as well. דיקא נמי
דקתני קונסין אותו עד עשרה בדמיו, dika nami dektani kotzin oto ad
asar bedamav, you can because we say you fine him for ten
times its value, and first of all, דמיו damav is in the
masculine, so it refers to the עובר, ubar, and also because it
says you give half of the value to the כהן Kohen or
the whole value to the כהן. Kohen. So you see we are
talking about the issue of the fetus, not of the mother, because
it is the בכור bechor that should be going to the כהן.
Kohen. שמע מינה, shma mina, you see from this. So we don't
have no, that's how we ended. So we tried to say the
opposite anyway. So you see that
you see again we cannot yet prove this question about selling a
cow for its children, whether that's included in the prohibition of selling
an animal to non-Jews. Now, we are going to put that aside
and get onto now this issue about fining somebody for having transgressed.
transgress that prohibition. Okay? And we said here that if you transgressed
and sold this animal to non-Jews, then you have to, but again
the concern here is that they'll use it on שבת Shabbat and
it will still be perceived of as a Jewish animal working on
שבת Shabbat or maybe it'll first only be on the loan and
it won't even be his yet and he'll work it on שבת
Shabbat and therefore they do not want you selling large animals meaning
like cows and horses or whatever to non-Jews, animals that could be
used to work on שבת. Shabbat.
Somebody sells something with a trial period. Right.
Right. Right. So when the non-Jew actually owns it, it's not a
problem. The problem is that there will be a trial period. Either
number one, there might be a perception that it's still the Jew's.
And number two is what the גמרא Gemara particularly emphasizes that there'll
be a trial period where it still is the Jew's and the
non-Jew is working it. And those are reasons in the גמרא. Gemara.
They don't sound like they fully explain this prohibition. There are other
possibilities that are thrown that are placed that are discussed there. But
for us, what's important is that there is this prohibition of selling
large animals to non-Jews and here we're seeing that there was a
fine that they made you pay up to ten times the value
to the non-Jew in order to buy it back. And now we're
going to focus, I just have to hold the questions, now we're
going to focus on this fine. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מסייע לריש לקיש. Mesayei le-Reish Lakish.
This supports ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש, De-amar Reish Lakish,
המוכר בהמה גסה לעובדי כוכבים, ha-mokher behemah gassah le-ovdei kokhavim, if you
transgressed this prohibition and you sell a large animal to a non-Jew,
קונסין אותו עד עשרה בדמיה. konsin oto ad asarah be-dameha. You make
them pay ten times the up to ten times the value in
order to buy it back. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara has
the question: דוקא או לא דוקא? Davka o lo davka? Literally ten
or not literally? Both in two ways. Do you have to go
as high as ten? Or the other way to say it is,
and is ten the limit? Okay? Or is ten just an exaggeration
and it's really not we don't mean it precisely? So the גמרא
Gemara says: תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. דאמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, De-amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, המוכר עבד לעובדי כוכבים, ha-mokher
eved le-ovdei kokhavim, if somebody sells a slave to a non-Jew, which
is also not allowed because it puts a slave, a slave in
Jewish ownership is obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. If he's owned by a
non-Jew, he's not able to perform מצוות. mitzvot. So and therefore it's
something we really don't like. And therefore, קונסין אותו עד מאה בדמיה.
konsin oto ad me'ah be-dameha. You make the owner pay up to
a hundred times the value in order to buy it back. So
רש"י Rashi says the point here is if ten was an exaggeration,
then we would not use different numbers to exaggerate differently. Okay? And
if one place we're saying ten and another place we're saying a
hundred, we actually mean them literally and actually to say that no,
you have to do more
for the buying back the slave than buying back the animal. So
you see, the גמרא Gemara says, so you see that these are
taken literally. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא שאני עבד דכל יומא
ויומא מבטלי ליה ממצוות. Lo shani eved de-khol yoma ve-yoma mevatlei leh
mi-mitzvot. A slave, maybe a hundred is literal because that's a real
problem because every day this slave who is obligated in מצוות mitzvot
is being prevented to do מצוות. mitzvot. So there we could be
literal and we could say you have to even go up to
a hundred. But when we say ten by an animal, maybe that's
just an exaggeration. Maybe we don't even mean it. Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara is still not sure whether the ten times for the
animal to buy it back is literal or not. So the גמרא
Gemara says: ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika de-amri, and some say that the debate
that the discussion happened this way. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish,
המוכר בהמה גסה לעובדי כוכבים קונסין אותו עד מאה בדמיה. ha-mokher behemah
gassah le-ovdei kokhavim konsin oto ad me'ah be-dameha. That ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says you pay up that you pay up to ten times
to buy that you pay up to ten times to buy back
the animal. תנן. Tenan. A hundred.
A hundred, I'm sorry. Right, this version has a hundred, up to
a hundred times. Thank you. תנן. Tenan. Now we're going to ask
from that from what we just taught before, which we said: והמוסר
לו בקבלה אף על פי שאינו רשאי קונסין אותו עד עשרה בדמיה,
ve-ha-moser lo be-kabbalah af al pi she-eino rashai konsin oto ad asarah
be-dameha, that if you give the animal to the non-Jew, you're not
allowed, you have to buy it back up to ten times the
value. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said a hundred, but here our
משנה Mishnah teaches ten. So how does ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish?
All right, thank you.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say, thank you very much
Michael, מכירה פסקה מיניה. mekhirah paskah mineih. Exactly. When ריש לקיש's Reish
Lakish case, you fully sold it, you fully divorced yourself from it,
so the fine is greater. You have to pay up to a
hundred times to get it back. קבלנות, Kablanut, in the case where
he's just raising the kids and you fundamentally still own the animal,
so לא פסקה מיניה, lo paskah mineih, you did not totally divorce
yourself from it and therefore we do not fine you as much
because you did not even as fully hand it over. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara says: דוקא או לא דוקא? Davka o lo davka?
So that deals with the contradiction of a hundred and ten. Now,
when we said a hundred, did he literally mean a hundred or
not literally mean a hundred? And here we're saying now a hundred
for buying back the animal. So תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, De-amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, המוכר
עבד לעובדי כוכבים. ha-mokher eved le-ovdei kokhavim. Now we have this same
way we had this version of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was a
hundred for the animal, in this version of the discussion, it was
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi had the ten for
the slave. It was the exact flip. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was
saying a hundred for the animal and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi was saying ten for the slave. המוכר עבד לעובדי
כוכבים קונסין אותו עד עשרה בדמיה. ha-mokher eved le-ovdei kokhavim konsin oto
ad asarah be-dameha. If you sell your slave to a non-Jew, you
have to buy him back up to ten times the value. So
the גמרא Gemara says: לא שאני עבד דלא הדר ליה. Lo shani
eved de-la hadar leh. No, there, the reason for the difference, they
both could be literal, right? Again our assumption is that they should
be the same. So if one is ten and one is a
hundred, I'm sorry, if one is ten and one is a hundred,
then our assumption is that if the number a hundred or whatever
ten is an exaggeration, you would not use a different number in
the two cases. So the fact that you're using a different number
shows that they are literal. Okay, but then the problem is, again,
okay, but if it's literal, then why is there a difference? Why
is one ten and the other a hundred? So the גמרא Gemara
says: No, here's the difference is. that by the slave, שאני עבד
דלא הדר ליה, shani eved delo hadar lei, when you buy back
the slave, it's a משנה Mishna in גיטין Gittin that if you
sold your slave to a non-Jew, there are two things. Number one,
because you cut him out of an obligation of מצוות, mitzvot, then
you, then if you buy him back, first of all you have
to try to buy him back, and if you buy him back,
he gets to go free. Okay, so it's really hard, we force
you to buy him back and then to free him, but all
of this is because you put him in this situation where he
can't do מצוות. mitzvot. So the גמרא Gemara is saying it might
be that here's the difference. It might be that the numbers, the
numbers are literal, 10 and 100 are literal. Why is there a
difference between the slave and the animal? Because the slave we're not
going to make you pay so much because you're going to have
to free him, so we're only going to demand up to 10.
The animal, which you get to keep, we're going to demand up
to 100. Now of course the point is, well okay that's true,
but the point is, one minute, if all you benefit in the
animal case is that you get to keep it, that means the
fine basically is 10 times, but for the animal we'll make you
go a little bit further because anyway you're going to get to
keep it. How much further should you go? One? So you go
11. Okay, because we're going to fine you 10 times you have
to lose, and then for the animal we'll make you go a
little higher because you get to keep it. So you go higher
one unit. One minute, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. So
the גמרא Gemara says בהמה, behema, שאני עבד דלא הדר ליה, shani
eved delo hadar lei, בהמה מאי טעמא? behema mai taama?
So why are you making him pay more for the בהמה? behema?
משום דקהדר ליה, mishum dekahadar lei, because you're going to get to
keep it. So fine, ליקנסיה טפי חד, liknesei tefei chad, pay one
more, pay one more times. Meaning if you're saying by the slave
you pay 10 times and you don't keep him, so the fine
is you have to lose up to 10 times the value. So
if that's what it means, then why aren't we saying the same
and why aren't we saying for the בהמה behema 11? You lose
10 times the value, the last one you pay is what its
value is and you get to keep it. אלא, Ela, here's the
reason. עבד מילתא דלא שכיחא היא וכל מילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו
בה רבנן. Eved milta delo shechicha hi vechol milta delo shechicha lo
gazru bah rabanan. A slave is something that is not so common
that you would sell a slave. It's much more common to sell
your animal to a non-Jew. It's much more common. So since it's
not so common, therefore the rabbis did not make as serious of
a fine. They were not לא גזרו lo gazru at all. They
were גוזר. gozer. No, they were גוזר. gozer. Right, so לא גזרו
lo gazru here does not really mean that they weren't גוזר gozer
at all, but it really means that they were not as concerned
about it. They didn't make as heavy of a fine. They saw
that the problem of selling these animals was a much more common,
a much more prevalent problem. So if something is a big problem,
you really try to put your foot down and you make a
very, very heavy fine. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is,
is that basically the גמרא Gemara saying is, you know, are these
literal or not literal? And if they are literal, then we have
to understand why we're treating a slave different than a בהמה. behema.
If they're not literal, then on the one hand you want to
say why did one say 10 and one say 100 since you
don't mean it literally anyway? But anyway, but if it's not literal,
we don't have to worry about these differences. But if it is
literal, we have to explain what these differences are based on. And
there's one approach is that a slave is a greater fine because
he's excluded from מצוות, mitzvot, but the other is we make a
greater fine by the animals because that was a much more prevalent
problem and we had to put our foot down. Two quick questions
before we go.
Was there any concern with that sounds like more like an economic
issue between the גוים goyim and
so that's an interesting question. And if you learn מסכת עבודה זרה,
Masechet Avodah Zarah, like I said, the explanation that it's a שבת
Shabbat concern does, you know, it seems not so much to fully
explain what's going on here. And in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah there
are larger concerns also about larger interactions of Jews and non-Jews. So
as I said, we learned this about a year ago when we
did עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So in six more years when we
get back to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, we can discuss the question
about the nature of the גזירה gezeira at greater length. But you
are right that the שבת Shabbat explanation does not seem to be
fully satisfying. There are other explanations that come up in the גמרא
Gemara as well.
What I was trying to understand was the two versions of רבי
יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. One was the first works
well, the לא גזרו lo gazru at the 10 times. What about
the version you said 100 times? Because that's what we started with.
אמר רבי יהושע. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua.
Right, so according to the version that they both say 100, then
it could be exaggerations and it could just be.
No, no, what about the fact that רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi one time at עבד eved is 100, and then
the next time he cited.
Right, so there are two different versions, same way there are two
different versions of ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. So and therefore there are
two different versions of what he said.
So it's either both 100 and yeah,
but we didn't but then we wouldn't have had a discussion. So
according to those that have a version of 100 for both or
10 for both, we didn't bother recording that because there wasn't anything
interesting to say. So we only have recorded the discussions around the
around the.
But it's מילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן, milta delo shechicha
lo gazru bah rabanan, but it's 100 times. That sounds like a
real.
So that might be exaggeration. Okay, so now we go on. Jewish
slave? Well, a slave, it's non-Jewish, but a non-Jewish slave owned by
a Jew went through a process of ברית מילה brit milah and
going into the מקוה mikvah and had a partial Jewish status and
obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. And that's why there's the problem about selling
him to the non-Jew. Okay, so now we go on. What?
So it's like
a yeah, like מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot asei shehazman grama, just
excluded from time-bound positive מצוות. mitzvot. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. חכמים אומרים כל זמן שידו ביד עובדי כוכבים. Chachamim omrim
kol zman sheyado beyad ovdei kochavim. Back to the central issue. People,
this is now very we need to focus because I need to
get done with this and because this is the very central point
about the non-Jewish ownership exempts you, like the חכמים, Chachamim, even partial
non-Jewish ownership exempts you from בכור, bechor, and that becomes the way
in which we don't give בכור bechor nowadays. So pay attention. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי יהושע. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua.
So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said, ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. ushneihem mikra
echad darshu. Both the חכמים Chachamim and
No, not the אשר יולד, asher yivaled, right? We saw it earlier,
it is
הקדשתי לי כל בכור בישראל. hikdashti li kol bechor b'Yisrael. I sanctified
for me all the firstborn in Israel. So the word in Israel
emphasizes Jewish ownership. Okay, so כל בכור, kol bechor, all the בכור.
bechor. רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri, בכור, bechor, the word בכור bechor by
itself, מקצת בכור, miktzat bechor, would have just meant suggested even partial
ownership, משמע. mashma. כתב רחמנא כל, katav rachmana kol, the entire, עד
דאיכא כוליה, ad d'ika kulei, and all has to be owned by
a Jew. כל בכור kol bechor has to be ישראל, Yisrael, the
entire בכור. bechor. רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi Yehuda savar, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says no, בכור כוליה בכור משמע. bechor kulei bechor mashma. If
it just said בכור bechor by itself, it would have suggested that
the entire בכור bechor has to be owned. כתב רחמנא katav rachmana
כל, kol, and it says all, and it already would have meant
the entire thing, so כל kol must mean אפילו כל שהוא. afillu
kol shehu. כל kol could mean כל kol could mean a כל
שהוא, kol shehu, any part of. כל kol can mean the entirety
or could mean even any part of. So the Rabbis read it
that the entire בכור bechor is ישראל Yisrael is חייב, chayav, and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it if even a part of, a
כל שהוא, kol shehu, a part of a בכור bechor is owned
by ישראל Yisrael is חייב. chayav.
All right. איבעית אימא, Iba'it eima, and if you want, דכולי עלמא
בכור רובא משמע. d'kulei alma bechor ruba mashma. בכור bechor would not
have there wasn't a debate whether it meant whether the word בכור
bechor by itself meant all, everything or a little, everybody would agree
that it meant partial, it would have meant the majority of it,
משמע. mashma. מר סבר כל משמע לטפויי אתא, Mar savar kol mashma
l'tapuyei ata, that when it says כל, kol, it says don't just
assume בכור bechor means partial בכור, bechor, כל kol means the entirety.
And now you're back to the idea of the entire בכור bechor
to fill it. ומר סבר לגרועי אתא. U'mar savar l'gru'ei ata. No,
the בכור bechor word by itself meant meant like half of a
בכור. bechor. כל kol comes to say not even half, even a
little bit, even a כל שהוא. kol shehu. So in the end
it's the same point, whether כל kol means the entirety or whether
כל kol means even a even a small portion. Okay. וכמה תשתף
של עובד כוכבים ותפטור מן הבכורה? V'kama tishatef shel oved kochavim v'tiptur
min habechora? How much ownership of a non-Jew exempts one from the
firstborn? So אמר רב הונא אפילו אזנו, Amar Rav Huna afillu ozno,
even the ear, even something totally trivial. Now, the basically that's interpreted
to mean something it's almost completely trivial, but it has to be
enough that were the non-Jew to take his portion, the animal would
be a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Okay. Now, it's interesting though, although
if the animal even was a genuine בעל מום, ba'al mum, you
would still give it to a כהן. kohen. Let the animal was
born with a cut-off ear. With a you would still give it
to a כהן. kohen. But nevertheless, here, and the גמרא's Gemara going
to essentially ask that in a minute. So we don't exempt you
because it says if it's a בעל מום. ba'al mum. We exempt
you because a non-Jew has ownership and that exempts you. But the
point is enough of an ownership that it has some significance. It
can't be completely trivial. If he owns a hair, okay, that would
not exempt you. But even an ear is enough. That's what that's
what whoever says. That's what yes, thank you. רב הונא Rav Huna
says this. Thank you. מתיב ליה רב נחמן. Metiv lei Rav Nachman.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman asks, ולימא ליה שקול אזנך וזיל. v'leima lei
shkol oznecha v'zil. Why not say to the non-Jew, take your ear
and go? Meaning, okay, you own an ear. It's not a if
it's a point one percent of the entire animal, you understand, he
has a partial ownership even a trivial ownership within the entire animal.
But if it's a specific part of the animal, why don't you
say he owns the ear, I own the rest, the rest is
obligated in בכור. bechor. Even if you were to take the ear,
I'd be obligated. So why so therefore you should still be obligated.
So איתמר. itmar. So he so he so he did not like
that. He thought basically and there's no answer to that. Meaning according
to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that's not enough to get you off
the hook. And now we're going to see two other opinions that
don't buy into the even an ear approach. איתמר, Itmar, it was
said, רב חסדא אמר דבר שעושה אותה נבילה. Rav Chisda amar davar
she'oseh otah neveilah. Only if the non-Jew owned if again, if he
owns a percentage of it and not a specific piece, everybody agrees
that gets you off the hook. Even if he owns point one
percent, he owns a portion of the entire thing. But the question
is if he owns a specific part, right, can we say, so
fine, I own the rest, I'm obligated in בכור bechor in the
rest or not? So here so here the first one yes says
even if he owns just an ear. Now we're saying no, if
he owns a specific part, it has to be a part that
were he to take it, the animal would be considered a נבילה.
neveilah. Essentially the animal would die. Like the lungs, the heart, the
head. Okay, that only then if it's a specific part, what gets
you off is only if it's a part that basically it could
be as if he owns the whole thing. As if it's a
טריפה, treifa, what well right, as opposed to a טריפה, treifa, which
is the next opinion. דבר שעושה אותה נבילה. Davar she'oseh otah neveilah.
ורבא אמר, V'Rava amar, רבא Rava says דבר שעושה אותה טריפה. davar
she'oseh otah treifa. Even if it's just a part that would not
kill it, but would make it a טריפה. treifa. So the גמרא
Gemara says במאי קמיפלגי, b'mai kamiflagi, what are they debating? So בטריפה
חיה, b'treifa chaya, whether a טריפה treifa could still live.
למאן דאמר דבר שעושה אותה טריפה, L'man d'amar davar she'oseh otah treifa,
רבא Rava that says if he owns a part that makes it
a טריפה treifa is enough to say that he's a serious owner,
קסבר טריפה אינה חיה. kasavar treifa einah chaya. If it were a
טריפה treifa it wouldn't live. So since he owns a part that
were it to take it, the animal would not necessarily die immediately,
but would would, you know, would eventually die, would die as a
result, then he owns a significant enough part to be considered a
real owner and to therefore exempt you. ולמאן דאמר דבר שעושה אותה
נבילה, U'l'man d'amar davar she'oseh otah neveilah, but the one that says
that's not enough, it has to be a part of the animal
that would kill
it, so... אבל טריפה חיה, aval tereifah chaya, the animal could still
live. And since the animal could still live, if he owns a
part that even were it to take it, the animal would survive,
he's not considered a serious enough owner. Again, this is only when
he owns a specific part. If he owns a percentage, then nobody
really debates. Now just one more point. I've been describing the נבילה
neveilah as it will kill the animal, but it doesn't exactly have
to be or kill the animal. For example, let's say he owns
the trachea. So if you were to move the trachea, it would
be impossible to do a שחיטה. shechitah. Okay? So that wouldn't exactly
necessarily, I mean, it would also kill the animal. But, but,
but, normally a נבילה neveilah is an animal that's dead. So what
does it mean עושה נבילה? oseh neveilah? עושה נבילה oseh neveilah is
either you would take it, it would kill it on the spot,
not just make it, not just be a fatal wound but literally
kill it, eventually cause it to die, which is טריפה, tereifah, or
it would prevent a שחיטה. shechitah. So that would be if he
owned like the trachea or the esophagus, but if that really is
different than saying kill it, I don't know. So you had a
question.
We are arguing about the definition of טריפה tereifah right now?
Well, we're arguing, I mean, like we learned at the beginning of
חולין, Chullin, we are arguing about whether when an animal, what do
you mean the definition?
What do you mean? Well, the argument is centered around טריפה חיה
tereifah chaya or טריפה אינה חיה, tereifah eina chaya, right?
Yes, it is. Why are you saying it isn't? So let's say
he owns the leg, and we know that if it's missing the
upper leg, it's a טריפה, tereifah, right? So, so רב Rav is
going to say, well, since were he to take that, the animal,
it would be a טריפה, tereifah, and since it's a טריפה, tereifah,
I know from my list of טרפות tereifos it's a טריפה. tereifah.
I don't just, and therefore, since I'm of the position, I take
the position טריפה חיה, tereifah chaya, I could also assume that if
he were to own that, the animal would eventually, would be, would
eventually die. And therefore it's a significant ownership. רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
was it רב נחמן? Rav Nachman? רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, I
know it's a טריפה, tereifah, but I don't think it'll kill the
animal. So therefore it's not a significant ownership. Okay. But so we're
arguing about the def-, but that's the definition of whether, they're not
arguing what's on the list of טרפות. tereifos. I mean, that might
be an outcome of the debate, but the גמרא Gemara more, you
know, in חולין, Chullin, did not focus so much on the question
of what's on the list of the טרפות, tereifos, but they did
focus on right, what, so yeah. So okay. If the answer, if
that's your question, then the answer is yes.
Okay. But everyone would agree that if you sold the בכור bechor
for its ear to a non-Jew, that that would enough to get
you off too, right?
What does it mean for its ear?
Like sort of like we had yesterday, a case like פר דקא,
per deka, I'm selling you a true for its ear.
No, but that's different. That's something that it's going to produce. This
is a portion of the thing itself. I can't sell you, I
can't sell you my book for the first page. I either sell
you the first page or I don't sell you the first page.
Okay? I, so yeah. Yes.
Does it always have to do with שחיטה? shechitah? In other words,
what if I have a cow for milk?
No, it doesn't. But here the point is, is his sense of
owning it mean that he has a, that he has a serious
owner? And the way to determine serious owner is what would be
the result if he took his portion away? Okay? And if the
animal would still survive, then he's not, then his ownership is not
that serious. Okay?
So it's just a sense of we can subdivide the cow per
se of, of, of like מעשה ידיה, ma'aseh yadeha, that's the entire
category of everything the animal produces, but I can subdivide its structure?
Yes. Sure. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, but that's not
our issue right now. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
אמרו רבנן קמי דרב פפא. Amru rabbanan kamei deRav Pappa. So the
רבנן rabbanan said over this debate to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Again,
רבנן rabbanan here usually means the rabbinical students, the תלמידים. talmidim. And
they said, and they had the following suggestion of how to reconcile
all the, of the major two big names. Meaning the טריפה tereifah
נבילה neveilah opinion, we understand their debate, but that's more like a
technical debate about how much is going to actually kill the animal.
Okay? But fundamentally they agree that it has to be an ownership
that the life of the animal is dependent on. Okay? But what
they're really debating is the camp, the first camp, that said even
the ear, which seems to say a trivial ownership, רב הונא. Rav
Huna. Now the students in the ישיבה yeshiva are going to try
to reconcile this. So let's take a look. So אמרו רבנן קמי
דרב פפא, Amru rabbanan kamei deRav Pappa, הא דרב הונא ורב חסדא
ורבא, had deRav Huna veRav Chisda veRava, those two camps, obviously רב
חסדא Rav Chisda and רבא Rava disagree in the נבילה neveilah טריפה,
tereifah, but the fundamental two camps, לא פליגי, lo pligi, maybe they
don't really debate. הא בו הא באמו. Ha bo ha be'imo. Maybe
it depends on whether you own the בכור, bechor, whether you own
the mother. For the ownership of the mother to get you off,
maybe it has to be a serious ownership. For the ownership of
the בכור, bechor, the actual animal that is what you give to
the כהן kohen or that has the מצוה mitzvah to redeem, there
maybe even a trivial ownership is enough to exempt you. That's a
nice, that's a nice split. So אמר ליה רב פפא, Amar leh
Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said back, מאי שנא בו
דבעינן כל בכור וליכא? mai shna bo deba'inan kol bechor velayka? No,
by the animal, if you say that even an ear exempts you,
by the בכור bechor because it says כל בכור, kol bechor, the
entirety of the בכור bechor has to be owned, and even an
ear, it's not the entirety. So if that's true, according to that
approach, באמו נמי, be'imo nami, they'd also say it by the mother.
בעינן כל מקנך תזכר, ba'inan kol miknecha tizachar, all of your cattle
you shall, sort of the males shall be בכור. bechor. So when
it refers to the ownership of the cattle, מקנך, miknecha, yours, it
also used the word כל. kol. So if כל kol means that
even a trivial ownership exempts you, if it's true by the בכור,
bechor, it's true by the mother. So the רב הונא Rav Huna
approach, and that's going to be important because we're going to פסקן
pasken the רב הונא Rav Huna approach basically, and therefore even just
selling the ear itself for the reasons we've been discussing, the ear
of an unborn fetus, you can do it as selling the mother
for the ear of the... unborn fetus, but it's very tricky. It's
a lot easier to just sell the ear of the mother, and
here we're saying רב הונא Rav Huna would apply it even to
the mother. Okay, so אלא לא שנא, ella lo shna, according to
רב הונא Rav Huna it doesn't matter, he would apply his thing
even to the mother. Now, מתקיף לה מר בר רב אשי: maskif
la Mar bar Rav Ashi: מאי שנא מדי פגם? maishna mide-fagam? Now
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi asks, this is similar
to what I said before, which is, look, let's say you say
that if the animal would die, that's enough of an ownership to
get you off the hook. He says, let's say the animal literally
did die. Let's say the בכור bechor died and it was a
stillborn. It would still have קדושת בכור, kedushas bechor, right? If it
was a donkey you'd have to redeem it, you'd have to bury
it if it was a sheep or whatever. It still has the
status of a בכור bechor even if it's dead. So, מה דתמן
פן המפלת? mah de-temen fen hamaplet? דאף על גב דלאו בני חיותא
נינהו, de-af al gav de-lav benei hiyusa ninhu, although they're not, they
don't have any life, they're not viable, קדשי, kadshei, they still have
sanctity of בכור. bechor. דאמר מר, de-amar mar, because we said, פטר
שגר בהמה, peter sheger behemah, the one that sort of breaches and
then is spewn forth from the בהמה. behemah. שגר דבהמה, sheger de-behemah,
even if it's like spewn forth in the sense of miscarriage. So
even
a miscarried animal has קדושת בכור. kedushas bechor. So therefore why do
you say ownership of a non-Jew gets you off the hook if
even if it were to die you would still be obligated? So
the גמרא Gemara says no. התם כיון דלא ערבו בה חולין חולין
קרינן בהו
בבהמה כל בכור. hasam keivan de-lo irvu beh hulin hulin karinan behu
bi-behemah kol bechor. There, since a non-holy ownership is not mixed in,
meaning the ownership of a non-Jew that is not obligated, since a
non-exempt, you do not have the problem of non-Jewish ownership, even if
the animal is still is not viable, we still say it is
a full בכור bechor of the בהמה, behemah, a dead one but
a full בכור. bechor. הכא כיון דערבי בהו חולין, hacha keivan de-arvi
beh hulin, here
since the non-obligated ownership, the ownership of a non-Jew is mixed in,
לא קרינן בהו כל בכור, lo karinan behu kol bechor, then you
don't have the full ownership. So basically saying you're right, if you
would be lacking that part it would still have the קדושה, kedusha,
but the reason you're exempt is not because it's as if it's
missing that part. The reason you're exempt is because there's non-Jewish ownership.
We are just saying there has to be a significant ownership. So
we're not saying an ear, but you understand the question because the
challenge to the ear position was, and big deal if it's missing
an ear. And the answer was, okay, but it's not missing an
ear. The point is there's non-Jewish ownership. So
that same challenge implicitly could be applied to the approach that says
the heart and the lungs. Because there too, even if it's missing
the heart and the lungs it's still obligated. So at the end
of the day, the reason you're exempt is not because it's as
if it's missing that part, the reason you're exempt is because of
the non-Jewish ownership, but the question is how much ownership is needed
to be considered significant. Okay, now,
רבי אלעזר לא עלה לבי מדרשא. Rabbi Elazar lo ala le-vei midrasha.
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar didn't get to the בית מדרש beis medrash
one day, and presumably he knew they were learning
בכורות. Bechoros. אשכחן Ashken לרב אסי. le-Rav Assi. He found רב אסי
Rav Assi who was in the בית מדרש. beis medrash. אמר ליה
מה אמרו רבנן בבי מדרשא? amar leh mah amru rabbanan be-vei midrasha?
What was the discussion in the
בית מדרש? beis medrash? אמר ליה הכי אמר רבי יוחנן אפילו מום
קל, amar leh hachi amar Rabbi Yohanan afilu mum kal, even if
it is a slight blemish. Okay, which means basically that even like
we've been saying, like the position of רב הונא, Rav Huna, that
even if the non-Jew only owns an animal, only owns a part
that would make a blemish, like an ear, presumably permanent, so here's
a qualification: ear does not mean anything, doesn't mean a toenail, doesn't
mean a hair. It has to be what is trivial but at
least enough that would make a blemish in the animal, that is
enough to exempt you. Essentially פסקן paskening like רב הונא Rav Huna
with a little clarification. Okay, והתנן, ve-ha-tenan, that's one thing. Now, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan also made another point, not relevant, but while we
were learning בכורות Bechoros he made another point, not relevant to our
immediate discussion. והתנן, ve-ha-tenan, he also pointed out that the משנה Mishnah
that says: רחל שילדה מין עז, rahel she-yalda min ez, if a
sheep gives birth to an animal that looks like a goat, ועז
שילדה מין רחל, ve-ez she-yalda min rahel, or a goat gives birth
to an animal that looks like a sheep, פטור מן הבכור. patur
min ha-bechor. The animal said,
the משנה Mishnah says that you're exempt from בכור bechor because it
does not look like its mother. But it says: ואם יש בו
מקצת סימנים, ve-im yesh bo miktzas simanim, if it looks somewhat like
its mother, let's say the wool is like a sheep but the
I don't know, the body shape or the legs or the tail
is like a goat. So it's somewhat, it looks a little bit
like its mother and a little bit not. So in that category,
חייב. hayyav. That category it has, it's obligated as בכור. bechor. So
if a sheep gave birth to an animal that looks like a
goat and a sheep, a hybrid, you are still obligated in בכור,
bechor, that's what the משנה Mishnah says. What did רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yohanan say? קם ליה רבי יוחנן ואמר מום קבוע הוא לשחוט עליו.
kam leh Rabbi Yohanan ve-amar mum kavua hu le-shahit alav.
It's true it's still a בכור, bechor, but the fact that it
looks like a half-goat half-sheep is a מום, mum, is a blemish.
Okay, it's a deformity. And therefore you give it to the כהן,
kohen, and the כהן kohen שוחט shechts it and eats it outside
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So it still has קדושת בכור, kedushas
bechor, but the hybrid nature of it makes it a מום. mum.
That was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yohanan's חידוש. hiddush. So those are the
two חידושים hiddushim of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yohanan. Now the גמרא Gemara
is going to analyze it. בשלמא מום קל, bishlama mum kal,
I understand the point of the חידוש hiddush of saying that even
if the non-Jew owns like an ear, enough to make even a
small blemish, it exempts you, קא משמע לן דרב הונא. kamashma lan
de-Rav Huna. That means that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan? *Rabbi Yochanan* is
פוסק *paskening* like רב הונא *Rav Huna*, that even a tiny ownership
of the non-Jew exempts you, ולאפוקי מדרב חסדא ורבה *ule-afokei mid'Rav Chisda
ve'Rabba* to reject the positions of רבה *Rabba* and רב חסדא *Rav
Chisda*. And that's very important הלכה *halacha*, that even a tiny ownership
and you don't need to non-Jew doesn't need to own enough to
make it a נבילה *neveila* or a טריפה *treifa*. אלא *Ella*, but
now we're going to digress for a few minutes before we get
back to our theme, אלא מום mum, קבוע מאי קא משמע לן
*Ella, mum kavua mai kamashmalan*? The idea that an animal that's half
goat half sheep is a sense of a מום mum. *mum*, a
blemish, what's the חידוש chiddush. *chiddush*? The חידוש chiddush. *chiddush* is כיון
דאשתני הוי ליה מומא *keivan de-ishtani havei lei muma*, because it's different,
it's a מום mum *mum*. This actually can be a very I
imagine contentious discussion which we can hold off hopefully till we get
to the פרק perek. *perek* that's all devoted to מומים *mumim*, but
the question about the concepts of perfection and blemish and so on.
Normally the idea blemish, the Torah doesn't spell it out. The Torah
says עור או פסח לא lo, יהיה בו מום mum *iver o
pise'ach lo yihiyeh bo mum*, you cannot have any blemish, blind or
lame etc. and doesn't spell out what the blemishes are. So normally
we interpret blemish as a sense of something is physically lacking, something
is missing and it won't grow back and something of that nature
or cut that won't heal, some type of something of that nature.
But also there's a concept of blemish that also has to do
with not something sort of removed or cut or lacking, but just
a deformity or something that's not normal, as we'll see in a
minute, one eye is very large, one leg is short, or some
types of things like that. There's different מומים *mumim* for כהנים Kohanim
*kohanim* and for בהמות *behemas* and it'll be a whole פרק perek
*perek* is going to be devoted to that. So here our discussion
is that how much is something if it just looks different, doesn't
look normal, is that something that you would actually call a blemish?
So this animal that's a hybrid, that looks like a goat but
has the sheep's wool, is that considered to be a blemish? Okay,
so that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if that's
his חידוש *chiddush*, that that's a blemish, that's not a חידוש *chiddush*.
So התנינא *hatanina*, we already taught that in a משנה Mishnah: *mishna*,
ופיו דומה כשל חזיר הרי זה מום mum *upiv domeh keshel chazir
harei zeh mum*. Let's say you have your sheep or whatever that's
mouth looks like a pig's mouth. So not something lacking, it just
looks like that of a different animal. So it says that's a
blemish. So obviously we know that idea that something that looks different,
not like its species, is a blemish. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says one minute, הכי תימא התם Hasam, נשתנה בדבר שאין במינו קדוש
בבכור bevchor *hachi teima hatam nishtaneh bedavar she-ein be-mino kadosh be-bechor*. There,
what it looks like is it has a characteristic of a species
that is not does not have the sanctity of בכור bechor *bechor*.
It has a characteristic of a pig. So that clearly would be
seen as a deformity specifically within the through the lens of the
question of בכור bechor. *bechor* having a characteristic of an animal that's
not in the category of בכור bechor. *bechor*. הכא *Hacha*, here, when
it looks like a half goat half sheep, נשתנה בדבר שבמינו קדוש
בבכור *nishtaneh bedavar she-be-mino kadosh be-bechor*. It looks the wrong characteristic is
still of an animal that's in the category of בכור bechor. *bechor*.
So it's a sheep that has some goat characteristics. But goats are
also in the category. So maybe that's not enough to say that
it's a deformity and that it's a מום mum. *mum*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says nevertheless, הא נמי nami, תנינא *hanami tanina*, we
also taught, עינו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה achat gdola v'achat ktana, *eino
achas gedola ve-achas ketana*, that if one eye is big and one
eye is small, ותנא *ve-tana* and what's the meaning there,
if one eye is either larger than the normal or the one
eye is smaller than the normal, one eye is normal but the
other is either too big or too small, that's considered a מום
mum. *mum*. What defines too big or too small? ותנא גדולה גדולה
כשל עגל *ve-tana gedola gedola keshel eigel*, big, as big as that
so you're talking about a sheep and if the eye is the
size of the eye of a calf and the other eye is
normal, that is a deformity. Or קטנה קטנה כשל אווז *ketana ketana
keshel avaz*. Or if it's small like the size of a duck,
then that's also a deformity if one and the other eye is
normal. So בשלמא קטנה כשל אווז אין במינו קדוש בבכור *bishlama ketana
keshel avaz ein be-mino kadosh be-bechor*. So the one that says as
small as a duck, you could say okay, that's because ducks don't
have the obligation of בכור bechor, *bechor*. And therefore it's a characteristic
of an animal that's not in the category of בכור bechor *bechor*.
But אלא גדולה *ella gedola*, the example of big is כשל עגל
*keshel eigel*, that of a calf. So יש במינו קדוש בבכור *yesh
be-mino kadosh be-bechor*, calves are obligated in בכור bechor *bechor*. So here
you have a sheep, one of its eyes is the size of
a calf, and we're calling it a מום *mum*. Now why? You
can't say because it has a characteristic of a non-בכור bechor *bechor*
animal. The size of the eye is still that of the size
of a calf, that is an animal that's in the בכור bechor,
*bechor* category. So you see even when it's like that of another
animal in the בכור bechor. *bechor* category, since it's not normal for
this species, it's not normal for a sheep, that's considered a deformity.
So similarly if a sheep has the wool of a goat or
the tail of a goat, even though they're both in the בכור
bechor *bechor* category, since it's not normal for a sheep, that would
be considered to be a מום *mum*. So why did רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* have to tell me that? I could have
figured it out myself. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says אלא לאו
ela lav, משום דאמרינן כיון דאשתני הוי ליה מומא *ella lav mishum
de-amrinan keivan de-ishtani havei lei muma*. You see that obviously the rule
is that once something is different, at least different enough that it's
not normal for this species, that's the case that we're dealing with.
So therefore that's considered a blemish. So why did we need רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan*? We could have figured that out. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא *lo*, no, we still needed רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, משום דהוי שרוע sarua *mishum de-havei sarua*,
I would have said that the case of different sized eyes is
a special example, is a special case. Because when the תורה lists
the blemishes of a כהן, Kohen, it speaks about שרוע sarua and
then there's a whole list. But שרוע sarua is understood to be
exactly this. One eye big and one eye small. Or one, you
know, one limb, limbs of different shapes, right? Not just size, like
limbs of different shapes and so on. So therefore it says like
this: normally yes, the eyes of different shapes is a מום, but
not because of a general principle that if it has a characteristic
of a different species it's a מום. Because of a specific מום
that is defined as misshapen limbs, different sized limbs. Okay, but if
it has the tail of a goat and the wool of a
sheep, that's not different sized limbs. Okay, that's just characteristics of a
different species. So we still don't know as a general principle that
to have a characteristic of a different species is a blemish. Maybe
there's a specifically a named blemish of שרוע sarua. which is the
problem. And the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra,
that actually makes sense that maybe that's what's going on here, that
it's a specific problem of שרוע. sarua, Why? דתנן, Ditnan,
we taught in the משנה: Mishnah מומין אלו בין קבועין בין עוברין
פוסלין. mumin elu bein kvuim bein ovrim poslin. All of these blemishes,
whether they are fixed or transitory, they invalidate the animal for being
brought as a קרבן. korban. If it's transitory, then after it goes
away you bring it as a קרבן, korban, but while it has
it, it cannot be brought. יתר עליהם אדם, Yeser aleihem adam, now
those are the blemishes the משנה says for animals. For humans, for
somebody to serve as a כהן Kohen in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, also can't have a blemish. So he has the following are
blemishes that are relevant for people that are not, that don't apply
to animals. What are they?
So regarding the eyes, שתים גדולות שתים קטנות, shtaim gdolot shtaim ktanot,
if both eyes are abnormally big or abnormally small. So now it's
saying by humans that's a problem, but by animals it's not. So
you see there's something special about different sized limbs which makes it
a bigger problem than just that it's abnormal. If the whole issue
was abnormal, then if both eyes were too big or both eyes
were too small, it would also be abnormal. So therefore since by
animals the only problem is different size, it's not the abnormality itself,
but it's the specific מום of different sized limbs. So the גמרא
Gemara says גבי אדם, gabai adam, by a man, by a כהן,
Kohen, how do we know it's a problem? דכתיב, De'chtiv,
we have a special verse that even applies to this case. It
says איש איש מזרע אהרן, ish ish mizerah Aharon, any person from
the seed of אהרן Aharon that has a blemish. And from there
we say דבעינן איש שוה בזרעו של אהרן. d'ba'inan ish shaveh b'zaro
shel Aharon. We need that it be a person that
has the characteristics of normal people, of everybody else. So even if
it's not different sized limbs, but it's just that both eyes are
abnormally big or abnormally small, that's not within the normal range of
normal sized eyes. Okay, I know, this is all I'm sure it's
very disturbing to people all these issues about normalcy and how do
we define it. Let's leave that until we get to that פרק.
Anyway, here the point is by כהנים kohanim. it has to be,
what do you call it, it has to be within, you know,
within what the range of most people have, within the standard deviation
of what most people have. And if both are too big or
both even both are too big or both are too small, it's
a problem. אבל בבהמה, Aval bivhema, but by animals, שתים גדולות שתים
קטנות נמי לא הוי מומא. shtaim gdolot shtaim ktanot nami lo havei
muma. If they're both too big or too small, it's not a
blemish. אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה, only if one is big and one
is small. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason that's different? אי
משום שינוי, Iy mishum shinui, if there's a general principle of, you
know, of things being abnormal by animals or things being characteristics of
other animals, אפילו שתים גדולות שתים קטנות, afilu shtaim gdolot shtaim ktanot,
even if they're both big or both small should be invalid. So
נמי, אלא לאו, it must be משום דהוי ליה שרוע. mishum de'havei
lei sarua. It is a unique מום of שרוע, of different sized
limbs. So now it's a little bit reversed. Before we said who
needs רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan We could have figured out on our
own that unusual characteristics is a blemish. But now we're saying the
opposite. Maybe unusual characteristics is not a blemish because both eyes big,
both eyes small is not a problem. Maybe the only thing that's
a problem is a specific type of thing that is called, you
know, abnormal limbs. So maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is even wrong.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, no. And this actually explains why
I needed רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan's Because you could have come to
that conclusion. You could have thought that
normal abnormalities is not a blemish and only the problem of misshapen
limbs. לעולם אימא לך משום שינוי, L'olam eima lach mishum shinui, that
really there is a general problem of different characteristics. ושינוי הוי מומא,
V'shinui havei muma,
and that is a blemish. ודקשיא לך, U'd'kashya lach, and your question
is אפילו שתים גדולות שתים קטנות, afilu shtaim gdolot shtaim ktanot,
then if that's true why isn't it a problem even if both
eyes are big or both eyes are small? התם, there, אם מחמת
בריאותא יתירתא, im machmat bri'uta yeteirta,
there, like there's a line essentially missing in the גמרא, Gemara it's
a little elliptical. It means that if they're both big or both
small, you could attribute it to, you know, basically standard deviation within
animals, at least it's saying, and at least you could say maybe
it's not considered like that of a different species is really the
point. Because you know, maybe it's not considered... Animals just very healthy
and had big eyes or didn't get enough nutrition and had small
eyes. And therefore only if one is big and one is small
do we say that that cannot be attributed to like within natural
variation of things that would happen to this species of animals. אם
משום בריותא אם מחמת בריותא Im mishum briyuta im machmat briyuta if
it was that the animal was particularly let's say healthy, then יתרתא
yitarta extra health essentially, תרוייהו בעו למהוי travaihu bau lemevei they both
should have been big. אם מחמת כחישותא Im machmat kachishuta if it
was because of malnutrition or weakness, יתרתא yitarta excessive, תרוייהו בעו למיחשי
travaihu bau lemichshei they both should have been small. So that ends
our discussion. Meaning, רבי יוחנן had created a חידוש. Okay, because רבי
יוחנן told me that having characteristics of a different species, even a
species that's כשר kasher בבכור is enough to exempt you. I would
not have known that, enough to be considered a מום. I would
not have known that. I would have said that it has to
be either characteristics of a non-בכור bechor species like of a duck
or whatever, a pig, or it has to be something that is
a specifically named blemish like something we know like
משופט. meshupat. Okay, but comes along רבי יוחנן says no, even a
characteristic that's not normal for this species is considered a blemish. The
idea of both eyes big, both eyes small, even though that's not
within the normal range, but nevertheless that's not unthought of in terms
of these animals if they're extra healthy, extra weak, etc. That's still
considered to be appropriate for this species. But if it's really a
characteristic that is not appropriate for the species, then that's considered to
be a blemish, that's רבי יוחנן's חידוש. Fine. That all has to
do with the פרק we're going to get up to in who
knows how much time, a month. What we really have to get
to is the end of this discussion about ownership of a non-Jew.
So let's take a look.
Okay,
ההוא גיורתא Hahu giyorta there was a convert דהוו מסרי ליה אחי
חיותא לפטומי dehavu masrei lei achei chayuta leftumei his brothers gave him,
his brothers the non-Jews, he was a convert, gave him their animals
to fatten and that he would get the firstborn. So he wanted
to know, is he exempt from the מצוה? mitzvah? And he would
get a portion of the kids. Is he exempt from בכורה bechora
because his brothers owned the animals themselves? אתא לקמיה דרבא Ata lekamei
deRava he came to רבא. Rava. אמר ליה Amar lei רבא Rava
said, לית דחש להא דרב יהודה דאמר שותפות עובד כוכבים חייבת בבכורה.
Leit dechash leha deRav Yehuda damar shutfut oved kochavim chayavet bechora. No,
nobody is concerned with רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda's position that says ownership
of a non-Jew is still obligated. As long as the non-Jew owns
it, you're exempt. Your brothers own the mother, so therefore you're exempt.
So now we've established non-Jewish ownership exempts you fully. Now we have
to figure out how much does the non-Jew have to own. רב
מרי בר רחל. Rav Mari bar Rachel. So רב מרי בר רחל
Rav Mari bar Rachel הויא ליה ההיא חיותא hava lei hahi chayuta
he had an animal. הוה מקני לאודנייהו לעובד כוכבים Hava maknei le'udnaihu
le'oved kochavim he sold the ear to a non-Jew. ואסר להו בגיזה
ועבודה Ve'asar lehu begiza va'avoda nevertheless, the animals that were born, even
though he sold the ear to a non-Jew, he treated as if
they were a בכור. bechor, He would not let them be shorn
or worked. ויהיב להו לכהני Veyahiv lehu lekhahanei and he gave it
to the כהנים. kohanim, So why'd he bother selling the ear? We'll
talk about that. And then the גמרא Gemara ends by saying וכליא
חיותא דרב מרי בר רחל Vechalya chayuta deRav Mari bar Rachel and
all his animals died out. He was punished by God. Now, what's
this all about? So first, before we get this punishment, let's figure
out why is he both selling the ear and treating the animal
as a בכור. bechor So the גמרא Gemara says וכי מאחר דאסר
להו בגיזה ועבודה Vekhi me'achar de'asar lehu begiza va'avoda if he's going
to forbid the animals in shearing, ויהיב להו לכהני veyahiv lehu lekhahanei
he gives them to the כהנים, kohanim he's treating them like a
בכור. You're prepared to treat them as a בכור, why are you
selling the ear? אמאי מקני לאודנייהו לעובד כוכבים Amai maknei le'udnaihu le'oved
kochavim why are you selling the ear to the non-Jew? So he
says, דילמא אתי לידי תקלה. Dilma ati lidei takala. So he's afraid
that the כהנים kohanim, aren't going to be careful. I'm prepared to
give my animal, my בכור to the כהנים, kohanim but they might
misuse them. They might shear them, they might שחט shacht them, not
wait till they have a מום. So what I'll do is I'll
give it to them but quietly make sure that they're not really
a בכור because I'm going to sell the ear to the
עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. So if the כהן kohen misuses it, he
won't transgress. Okay, so he wanted to protect the כהן, kohen, he
didn't trust the כהנים to treat the בכור properly. So the גמרא
says now, אי הכי ei hachi says the גמרא מאי טעמא כליא
חיותא דרב מרי? mai ta'ama khalya chayuta deRav Mari?
So now, so why was he punished? What did he do that
was wrong? They weren't בכור, what was the big deal? And he
was being very פרום. frum. The גמרא says no, you think you're
being פרום, frum, but משום דמפקי להו מקדושתייהו. mishum demapkei lehu mikedushatayhu.
You are taking the animals out of the opportunities, you're taking them
out of their קדושה kedusha to be a real בכור. That's what
he did. I know, we're going to get there. So the גמרא
says והאמר רב יהודה מותר לאדם להטיל מום בבכור
קודם שיצא לאויר העולם Veha'amar Rav Yehuda mutar le'adam lehatil mum be'bechor
kodem sheyetzei le'avir ha'olam that doesn't רב יהודה Rav Yehuda say you
can stick your hand into the womb of a pregnant cow and
create a blemish in the בכור because before it gets to קדושה
kedusha of בכור you can create a blemish because it doesn't yet
have it hasn't been born yet and therefore it won't have to
be brought as a קרבן korban and you'll be able to שחט
shacht it and eat it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. How
is this any different? Here too the animal hasn't been born yet,
you're just selling an ear of the mother, so you're just preventing
it ahead of time. So the גמרא says התם מקדושת
מזבח קמפקי ליה Hatam mikedushat mizbe'ach kamapkei lei when you make a
blemish you prevent it from the sanctity of the altar. מקדושת כהן
לא מפקי ליה. Mikedushat kohen lo mapkei lei. It's not that it's
not a בכור, it's just and the כהן kohen still has it
and it still has the קדושה kedusha and you still don't shear
it, so it still is a בכור just doesn't have to be
brought to the altar. You haven't totally removed it. והכא Vehakha what?
Why would you do that?
Because nowadays if it doesn't have a blemish you can't do anything
with it.
Why would you put your hand in
there and create...
Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says הכא
*hacha*, הכא *hacha* here, אפילו מקדושת כהן קמפקי ליה *afilu mikdushat kohen
kamafkei lei*, you completely exclude it, it doesn't even have the sanctity,
it's completely not a בכור *bechor*, the firstborn once you sell the
ear. So that's why he was punished. ואיבעית אימא *Ve'iba'it eima*, and
if you want you could say רב מרי בר רחל *Rav Mari
bar Rachel* ידע לקנויי קנין גמור *yadav laknuyei kinyan gamur*. He knew
how to do a transaction that really would have worked. Okay, now
maybe why is it complicated? So maybe it's because he was only
selling the future children and not the actual ear, the mother itself.
Anyway, he knew how to do it properly. וחזו ליה אינשי אחריני
ואזלו ועבדו *Vechazu lei inchei achrinei ve'azlu ve'avdu*. Other people saw, oh,
that's a great trick, and they followed the idea and they went
ahead and they sold the ear of their animal, of their cow,
but they didn't do it correctly and therefore they were really obligated
but they didn't because they didn't really know how to do the
transaction that it would work. וסבר רב מרי מילתא הוא דעבידי *Vesavar
Rav Mari milsa hu de'avidi*, and רב מרי *Rav Mari* felt that
they were just doing their transaction incorrectly or maybe for just a
verbal transaction, ואתי בהו לידי תקלה *ve'asi bohu lidei takala*, and therefore
and it was going and it would have led to, you know,
would have led to error. So therefore because it would have led
to error, therefore he went ahead and even after he had sold,
so one minute, so and therefore one minute, so even after he
had sold his,
one minute, is this explaining, one minute,
why he was punished? Why he was punished or why he went
ahead and gave it to the כהן *kohen* even at, no, it
has why he was punished because but then it says וסבר רב
מרי *vesavar Rav Mari*,
וסבר *vesavar*, the person would think, the other people,
oh, I'm sorry, רב מרי *Rav Mari*, oh, I'm sorry, thank you,
thank you very much, you're right, I misread it. וסבר *Vesavar*, so
other people saw,
interpreted that רב מרי מילתא הוא דעבידי *Rav Mari milsa hu de'avidi*,
I'm not sure, anyway, that they just thought that he did it
verbally, ואתי בהו לידי תקלה *ve'asi bohu lidei takala*, and other people
therefore were misled. So he was punished because it led to other
people doing the same thing but doing it incorrectly and thinking that
they got a בכור *bechor*. Now this is very important and I
know we're already over but I have to say this, it's very
important because this is what we do nowadays. The way we get
out of בכור *bechor* is because you don't want to have to
deal with the קדושה *kedusha*, right? Not just you don't want to
give it to the כהן *kohen*, which is maybe partially true, but
you don't want to have to deal with the קדושה *kedusha*, wait
till it gets a מום *mum*, it leads to, to me, to
a lot of transgression and sin. So we sell the ear to
a non-Jew. So תוספות *Tosafot* says, how did we sell the ear
to a non-Jew if רב מרי *Rav Mari* here was punished? So
he basically has two answers. The answer number one is that's because
they, a, knew how to look at blemishes and they were, they
had a society they would have been careful, etc., and that was
the better alternative religiously was to wait till it got a blemish
and to deal with it appropriately. Nowadays we don't know how to
assess blemishes, number one. Number two, we're very likely to, to, to
err and to misuse the בכור *bechor* and therefore the better religious
thing is to sell the ear and to get out of it
rather than have to deal with the dangers of dealing with the
בכור *bechor* and all of the status. The other thing he says
is the second answer says that the problem was was that just
people didn't know how to do it properly. So and didn't say
he was punished for the actual selling it. The problem was that
people misinterpreted. So as long as we're making sure that we're doing
it properly, it's not an issue. So just out of, just and
just to show you how this gets translated after hearing how רב
מרי בר רחל *Rav Mari bar Rachel* got punished, שלחן ערוך *Shulchan
Aruch* says the following. בזמן הזה מצוה לשתף עם עכו"ם קודם שיצא
לאויר העולם *Bazman hazeh mitzvah leshatef im akum kodem sheyeitzei la'avir ha'olam*,
it's a מצוה *mitzvah* to make a non-Jew a partial owner in
the mother, כדי לפטרו מן הבכורה *kedei lifto'o min habechora*, אף על
פי שמפקיע קדושתו *af al pi shemafki'a kedushato*, even though you're preventing
the animal from ever having קדושה *kedusha*, הכי עדיף טפי *hachi adif
tfei*, that is better, כדי שלא יבא לידי מכשול ליהנות ממנו בגיזה
ועבודה *kedei shelo yavo lidei michshol lehannos mimenu begiza va'avoda*, in order
that you should not come to transgression. So although רב מרי בר
רחל *Rav Mari bar Rachel* was punished, okay, he presumably had better
alternatives or could have done it better, but we actually say for
us this is the better alternative and this actually gets framed actually
as a מצוה *mitzvah*. I will also tell you that it raises
questions about how do you do a transaction with a non-Jew that
is binding? This comes up in a few very important halachic places
that you're certain is halachically binding. One place is selling חמץ *chametz*,
you gotta make sure it really is a transaction that's halachically binding
because it's not clear which forms of transactions work between Jews and
non-Jews to make it halachically binding. And the other place is here
by, by selling the בכור *bechor*, right? According to the end state
of the גמרא *Gemara*, the whole problem was that people weren't sure
how he was doing the sale. So you have to know how
to do the sale. So just to give you a sense about
the amount of discussion there is on how to do a binding
sale with a non-Jew, here, can you see all this small print
here and all this small print here? That's all a distillation of
the responsa about how to do sales to the non-Jew and what
if they were done this way without that way and is it
still binding and are you still exempt from בכורה *bechora*. Okay, but
with this גמרא *Gemara*, we nowadays get out of the whole מצוה
*mitzvah* of בכור *bechor*.
Same thing by שמיטה *Shemita*, by the way, same kind of discussion.
All right.